[
  {
    "question": "The vessels that operate on specific route on high seas and oceans are",
    "option_a": "Coastal Liners and Cargo Liners",
    "option_b": "Cargo Liners and Tramp liners",
    "option_c": "Passenger liners and Tramp liners",
    "option_d": "Passenger Liners and Cargo Liners",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "ocean liners are vessels that operate on specific on high seas and oceans and they operate on fixed time schedule"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an oil exploring and mining company builds a health centre in one community where at operates, such a company is",
    "option_a": "Carrying favour from local people",
    "option_b": "finding a way to spend excess profit",
    "option_c": "Fulfilling part of its social responsibility",
    "option_d": "Investing its idle fund",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "the health centre the company built is a social amenity and in doing so it is fulfilling parts of is social responsibility to the most community in which it is doing business."
  },
  {
    "question": "the world tourism organization has it headquarters in",
    "option_a": "New York",
    "option_b": "Madrid",
    "option_c": "Paris",
    "option_d": "London",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "is correct the headquarters of the world tourism organization is located in Madrid, Spain"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cheque drawn by a bank official on the bank’s deposit in another bank on a customer’s deposit in another bank",
    "option_a": "Bank draft",
    "option_b": "Bankers’ order",
    "option_c": "Promissory note",
    "option_d": "Travelers cheque",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "it is an order by the customer requesting the bank to transfer certain amount from the customer’s account to another bank account, so it is a standing order."
  },
  {
    "question": "The development of commerce in west Africa was not hampered by",
    "option_a": "Inadequate capital",
    "option_b": "Inadequate means of transportation",
    "option_c": "Insurance",
    "option_d": "Low savings",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is classified as an immaterial want?",
    "option_a": "Protection",
    "option_b": "Raw materials",
    "option_c": "Machines",
    "option_d": "Goods and Services",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "Protection it is not meant to increase our materials wealth but to make our lives worth living"
  },
  {
    "question": "In product pricing, which of these elements need more consideration than others?",
    "option_a": "The cost of producing the product",
    "option_b": "The economic conditions in the market",
    "option_c": "the demography of the buyers of the product",
    "option_d": "The demand for the product",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "what the form consider first and most is the cost of production i.e. the cost of producing the product as this determines the price at which the product will be sold."
  },
  {
    "question": "The major determinant of fire insurance premium is the",
    "option_a": "Owner of the property",
    "option_b": "usefulness of the property to the owner",
    "option_c": "Type and structure of the property to be insured",
    "option_d": "extent of fire damaged anticipated.",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "the type and structure of the property will determine the value of the property since the value of the property will have to be considered by the insurance company before the contract will be entered into by both parties."
  },
  {
    "question": "The agency in Nigeria which ensure that products conform to government quality specification is the",
    "option_a": "Nigerian consumers’ association",
    "option_b": "Manufacturers' Association of Nigeria",
    "option_c": "Standard Organization of Nigeria",
    "option_d": "Nigerian Chamber of commerce",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "the standard organization of Nigeria is the organization saddled with the responsibility of ensuring that goods or products conform to government quality specification"
  },
  {
    "question": "Citizens are against privatization mainly because of",
    "option_a": "Ineffective Management",
    "option_b": "The likely hood of monopoly",
    "option_c": "Increased price of good and services",
    "option_d": "The ration dilation of organizations.",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "privatization of government owned companies will bring about increase in prices of goods and services nd this situation will definitely not make the citizens to be happy with the issue of privatization and as such they will be against it."
  },
  {
    "question": "A market where new shares are tracked is known as",
    "option_a": "Primary Market",
    "option_b": "Stock Exchange",
    "option_c": "Secondary Market",
    "option_d": "Money Market",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "The primary market provide avenue where companies and organization can issue new securities in order to raise fund."
  },
  {
    "question": "The application of division of labour would generally bring about",
    "option_a": "Increase in quantity of goods and services",
    "option_b": "Increase in variety of goods and services",
    "option_c": "Cheapness of goods and services",
    "option_d": "Cost efficiency in the production of goods and series.",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "Division of labour ensure that there more hands involved in the production of a particular, commodity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The computer using linear integrated circuit technology complied with quantification of data in term of length and distance is",
    "option_a": "Main frame Computer",
    "option_b": "Digital Computer",
    "option_c": "Analogue Computer",
    "option_d": "Hybrid Computer",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "mainframe computer is the largest compute which his all the features stated above."
  },
  {
    "question": "The internet is a system of telecommunication used for",
    "option_a": "Sending electronic message",
    "option_b": "Communicating messages through telegrams",
    "option_c": "Communicating long-distance",
    "option_d": "Sending and renewing text message",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "the devices involved in the internet are electronic devices, the internet is used for sending electronic message."
  },
  {
    "question": "The implied provisions in every sale of goods as contained in the sale of goods act of 1893 are conditions and",
    "option_a": "Guaranties",
    "option_b": "Warranties",
    "option_c": "Sureties",
    "option_d": "Consideration",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "warranties is any stipulation which is not of such importance as to go to the root of the contract. The breach of warranties gives the other party a right to claim for damage but not to reject the contract."
  },
  {
    "question": "Communication enhances business activities by",
    "option_a": "facilitating interaction between producers",
    "option_b": "Facilitating interaction among media houses",
    "option_c": "ensuring the movement of good forms the producer to the consumer",
    "option_d": "keeping the goods safe until they and needed",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "through communication the producer interacts with the consumer through advertising."
  },
  {
    "question": "The effective and efficient delivery of the desired satisfaction by a firm is said to be the practice of",
    "option_a": "Product concept",
    "option_b": "Marketing concept",
    "option_c": "Distribution concept",
    "option_d": "Price concept",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "marketing concept is aimed at ensuring the satisfaction of the consumer i.e. the buyer or consumer is the vocal point in marketing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The document that gives an important freehand to obtain goods form any manufacturer is",
    "option_a": "A closed indent",
    "option_b": "A consular invoice",
    "option_c": "A freight note",
    "option_d": "An open indent",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "Are open indent allows the importer to purchase goods form any supplier since the of the producer is not specified"
  },
  {
    "question": "Company has an authorized capital of 100millon shares at N1 per share, out of which 50 million shares have been issued and fully paid-up the remaining 50 million shares have",
    "option_a": "Not yet been issued",
    "option_b": "Been applied for but not issued",
    "option_c": "Not been paid-up",
    "option_d": "Been issued but have not been paid-up",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "not of the 100 million shares, 50 million has issued and fully paid, this means that the remaining part of the shares has not been issued."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes an invoice?",
    "option_a": "Contractual agreement for the sale of goods",
    "option_b": "Document specifying quantity, description, prices and total value of purchase .",
    "option_c": "Receipt containing necessary information about the goods.",
    "option_d": "Letter specifying the contractual sales of goods between two parties",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "an invoice is a document sent by the seller to the buyer showing the full details of gods sold such as quantity, description, price, discount and the total amount t o be paid."
  },
  {
    "question": "A direct service is rendered by",
    "option_a": "State counsels",
    "option_b": "Civil servants",
    "option_c": "Police",
    "option_d": "Family doctor",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "family doctor is rendering a private service to the family and paid for by the family. Options A, B and C are not correct because the service they rendered is paid for by the government from taxes paid by member of the public"
  },
  {
    "question": "The business organization established mainly for the purpose of carrying out specific assignment for a specific duration is a",
    "option_a": "Partnership",
    "option_b": "Company",
    "option_c": "Joint venture",
    "option_d": "Co-operative society",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "joint ventures are established in order to accomplishment a specific purpose after the ventures cease to operate ones the purpose is accomplished."
  },
  {
    "question": "Second-tier securities market differs from the first-tier securities market in that the former is",
    "option_a": "highly restricted",
    "option_b": "Regulated by SEC",
    "option_c": "Regulated by NIPC",
    "option_d": "less restricted.",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "of the strongest condition attached to the quoting of shares of compares under the first-tier securities market is very strict."
  },
  {
    "question": "Inbound tourism occurs when",
    "option_a": "non-resident s of a country travel within it.",
    "option_b": "non- resident of a country travel to other countries",
    "option_c": "resident of a country travel within it",
    "option_d": "Residents of a country travel to other countries.",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "it involves the movement of tourist within their country of residence tourist resident in Nigeria for instance travelling within."
  },
  {
    "question": "A machine which enables sales without the physical presence of sales attendant is a",
    "option_a": "Telex Machine",
    "option_b": "Fax Machine",
    "option_c": "Vending Machine",
    "option_d": "Computer machine",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "the vending machine is a retails machine that release the product to the tune of the amount of money slotted into the machine and the product indicated by the consumer."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a typical manufacturing enterprises, the line function is performed by the",
    "option_a": "Public relations department",
    "option_b": "Marketing Department",
    "option_c": "Estate or Properties Department",
    "option_d": "legal Department.",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "the marketing department does public relations i.e the public relations department is part of the marketing department"
  },
  {
    "question": "The body regulating the sale and purchase of shares in Nigeria is the",
    "option_a": "Corporate affair commission",
    "option_b": "Securities and exchange commission",
    "option_c": "Securities and exchange tribunal",
    "option_d": "Nigerian stock exchange",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "the securities and exchange commission is the regulatory apex organization of the Nigerian capital market."
  },
  {
    "question": "A memorandum of association is applicable to a",
    "option_a": "partnership",
    "option_b": "sole trader",
    "option_c": "joint stock company",
    "option_d": "public corporation",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "it is joint stock Company that prepare memorandum of association during the course of registering the company it is also known as Limited Liability Company."
  },
  {
    "question": "An agent who takes title to goods and has authority to buy and sell on behalf of another is",
    "option_a": "A jobber",
    "option_b": "A broker",
    "option_c": "A factor",
    "option_d": "An auctioneer",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "As a jobber takes title to the goods and has authority to buy and sell or behalf of another"
  },
  {
    "question": "Resource committees into the production of relatively few commodities is known as",
    "option_a": "Production",
    "option_b": "Specialization",
    "option_c": "Creation manufacturing",
    "option_d": "Manufacturing",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "Specialization is the act of concentrating resources and efforts into the production of relatively few commodities by an individual, firm or a country"
  },
  {
    "question": "The measure of independence available to the individual business units that come together is the main difference between",
    "option_a": "vertical and horizontal integration",
    "option_b": "Mergers and Acquisition",
    "option_c": "Consortium and imagination",
    "option_d": "Trust and Cartel",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "in merger and acquisition the firms coming together are independent of one another as is not correct because they are types of merge."
  },
  {
    "question": "In the permanent storage device, DASD means",
    "option_a": "Data Access Systems Device",
    "option_b": "Direct Access Systems Device",
    "option_c": "Data Access Storage Device",
    "option_d": "Direct Access Storage Device",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "it is a magnetic storage unit, in which the access mechanism and storage medium can be positioned directly at the addresses sought to read or write specific data items."
  },
  {
    "question": "The development of commercial activate in Nigeria was harnessed by",
    "option_a": "A good storage system",
    "option_b": "Availability of market",
    "option_c": "Increase in production",
    "option_d": "Activities",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "Is good storage system makes it possible for goods produced ahead of time to be stored until they are needed."
  },
  {
    "question": "The forum for the selling and buying of securities of small and medium companies is called.",
    "option_a": "Securities and Exchange Commission",
    "option_b": "Second tier Security Market",
    "option_c": "Foreign exchange Market",
    "option_d": "Second tier foreign Exchange market",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "it is a market for buying and selling shares of small and medium scale companies,"
  },
  {
    "question": "The external environmental factors that affect a business cooperation are",
    "option_a": "Economic, Social and legal",
    "option_b": "Political, Culture and Labour",
    "option_c": "Competition, Labour and Political",
    "option_d": "Competition, Industry and Product.",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "these elements affect the operation of business eternally factor which can affect the operations of the business."
  },
  {
    "question": "The difference between a private are public limited liability company is that the former",
    "option_a": "Is unable to declare and pay dividend.",
    "option_b": "Has a higher number of share holder",
    "option_c": "Is unable to offer shares to the public.",
    "option_d": "pays higher salaries to its member",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "the former does allow members of the public to subscribe to its shares."
  },
  {
    "question": "A type of long-term loan granted to companies with fixed interest rate as well as with redeemable and irredeemable features is referred to as projects.",
    "option_a": "debenture",
    "option_b": "a bond",
    "option_c": "a term loan",
    "option_d": "an overdraft",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "it is a debenture that is grow under a seal by company in acknowledgement of a debit undertaking to repay the stated amount or sum on or before a certain date and to pay a fixed rate of interest. There are redeemable and irredeemable debenture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The circulating capital of a business enterprise is classified into",
    "option_a": "Cash, work-in-progress and debtors",
    "option_b": "Cash, Vehicles, land and building",
    "option_c": "debtors, stocks of raw materials and fitting",
    "option_d": "Prepayments, debtors and equipment",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "circulating capital is the amount of many used for day-to-day running of the business. It is the capital available to a firm for general purpose after current liabilities have been deducted. It is the excess of current liabilities over the current liabilities"
  },
  {
    "question": "Use the information below to answer this question.<br> Mammy Plc, whose nominal capital is made up of 5,000,000 ordinary shares at 50K each, decide to offer 80% of it to the public and realized only 50% of the amount due.<br> what is the company authorized share authorized share capital?",
    "option_a": "N4,000,000",
    "option_b": "N5,000,000",
    "option_c": "N7,500,000",
    "option_d": "N2,500,000",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "From the calculation made we arrived at the answer and using the formula.<br> Nominal capital is the same as authorized x capital<br> The price per share is 50K<br> ∴ Authorized share capital<br> =N5000000 x 0.50K<br> = N2,500,000"
  },
  {
    "question": "A bond which attracts interest but leaves the capital repaid is referred to as",
    "option_a": "A redeemable bond",
    "option_b": "An irredeemable bond",
    "option_c": "A development bond",
    "option_d": "A long-term loan",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "the bond is per petrol, which is until death. The issuing authority or entity pays a specific interest rate periodically but provides no data on when the principal will be returned."
  },
  {
    "question": "The document issued to a port authority when a good are deposited is a",
    "option_a": "dock warrant",
    "option_b": "Dock landing account",
    "option_c": "Ball of sight",
    "option_d": "Bill of landing note",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "It is a document that shows that the goods are stored in the warehouse and it entitles the holder to take possession of the goods."
  },
  {
    "question": "The business environment that takes into cognizance the age distribution ethnic mix and educational level of the consumer is",
    "option_a": "Natural Environment",
    "option_b": "Cultural environment",
    "option_c": "Economic environment",
    "option_d": "Demographic Environment",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "demographic environment that put into consideration the composition of the population of the consumers, it determines the quantity of goods to be produced."
  },
  {
    "question": "The term 4 net 7 on an invoice means that",
    "option_a": "4% surcharge will be made unless payment is made within seven days",
    "option_b": "4% discount will be allowed on the price charged only if the good are bought within seven days",
    "option_c": "4% discount will be allowed on the price charge if payment is made after seven days",
    "option_d": "4% discount will be allowed on the price charged if payment is made price charged if payment is made price charged if payment is made within seven days.",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "the discount is allowed to encourage seller prompt payment for the goods bought by the buyer."
  },
  {
    "question": "Musa obtains wool from his sheep, spins and transform it into cloth which he sells to consumers, this is a form of",
    "option_a": "Vertical integration",
    "option_b": "Horizontal integration",
    "option_c": "Forward Integration",
    "option_d": "Background integration",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "this integration involves the coming of two or more firms at different production stage in the same industry. The production of wool is one stage in the production of cloths while spinning and transformation of the wool into clothes is another stage in the production of clothes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The principle of subrogation stated that",
    "option_a": "An insured person should be indemnified to the time of the amount insured",
    "option_b": "An insurance company constant in lace of the insured in dealing with third party.",
    "option_c": "Only a person who is likely to suffer loss hold take out an insurance cover",
    "option_d": "There must be accuse connection between the actual loss suffered and risk insure",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "The option is in line with the principle of subrogation"
  },
  {
    "question": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \n\n\\text{Opening stock} & 1800  \\\\\n\n\\hline \n\n\\text{Purchases} & 2800 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Sales} & 800 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Closing stock} & 800 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Carriage on sale} & 500 \\\\\n\n\\end{array}\\)<br> Calculate the value of the unused stock",
    "option_a": "N320",
    "option_b": "N350",
    "option_c": "N500",
    "option_d": "N800",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "Closing stock for the year of an accounting period is also regarded as unused stock."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given<br> \\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \n\n\\text{Opening stock} & 50,000 \\\\\n\n\\hline \n\n\\text{Purchases} & 200,000 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Sales} & 350,000 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Closing stock} & 80,000 \\\\\n\n\\end{array}\\)<br> What is the cost of good sold?",
    "option_a": "N200,000",
    "option_b": "N190,000",
    "option_c": "N170,000",
    "option_d": "N175,000",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "The cost of goods sold is calculated through the formula below <br> opening stock + purchases – closing stock.\n\nIf we go by the formula above it is\n\n N50,000 + N 200,000 - N80,000 which is equal to N170,000."
  },
  {
    "question": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \n\nN & N  \\\\\n\n\\hline \n\n\\text{Capital 8000} & \\text{Plant and machinery5000}\\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Net profit 4000} & \\text{Motor Van 4500} \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Drawings 200} & \\text{Stock 2000} \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Creditors 2000} & \\text{Debtors 1000} \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Accurals 300} & \\text{Banks 100} \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n        & \\text{Cash 600} \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n14100 & 14100 \\\\\n\n\\end{array}\\)<br> What is the current ration?",
    "option_a": "4 : 1",
    "option_b": "5 : 1",
    "option_c": "3 : 1",
    "option_d": "2 : 1",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \n\n\\text{Name} & \\text{Insure amount} & \\text{Actual value} & \\text{Actual loss} \\\\\n\n\\hline \n\n\\text{Mr A} & 30,000 & 100,000 & 40,000 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Mr B} & 40,000 & 120,000 & 50,000 \\\\\n\n\\hline\n\n\\text{Mr C} & 50,000 & 15,000 & 70,000 \\\\\n\n\\end{array}\\)<br> If Mr A takes a fire insurance policy with average clause, his compensation will be",
    "option_a": "N15,000",
    "option_b": "N20,000",
    "option_c": "N12,000",
    "option_d": "N25, 000",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "Since the policy is with average clause the formula used in calculating his compensation is<br> \\(\\frac{\\text{Amount insured x total actual loss}} {\\text{Total actual value of property}}\\)<br> By this formula the compensation will be<br> Amount insured = N30,000<br> Amount loss = N40,000<br> Actual Value = N100,000<br> =\\(\\frac{30,000 \\times 40, 000}{100,000}\\)<br> = \\(\\frac{1200000000}{100,000}\\)   = 12,000"
  }
]